Hypertext Transfer Protocol, HTTP, is the
main protocol used for webpages, such as the
one we see.
With a heightened awareness of security in
data transfers, most webpages use the secure
version of HTTP, HTTPS, as we see here.
The difference between HTTP and HTTPS is simply
this: Data transmitted over HTTP is not encrypted.
Data transmitted over HTTPS is encrypted.
Any sensitive data transmitted over the internet
should be encrypted, and thus HTTPS should
always be used.
A protocol in the same realm as HTTP and HTTPS
is FTP, File Transfer Protocol.
This protocol is often used to upload and
download files to and from a web server.
For port numbers, HTTP transmits over port
80, HTTPS port 443, and FTP port 21.